very good and welcome one more day to
see take for those of you who are new
to the channel here we talk about software and
technology and specifically in this
series we talk about design patterns
we are going to explain one by one each
design pattern looking at their uses and
explaining them with examples if you still don't
know what a design pattern is I'll
leave the index of the series
up here and in the description then the
pattern in this video is the
abstract factory pattern the abstract factory
is a pattern that is closely related
to the factor pattern and hence the
names are also similar so
if you haven't seen what the factory pattern is I
advise you to watch that video first and
then watch this one again
perfect because with this we can go
a little deeper into the
abstract factory pattern and for that we are going to
talk about a game that could be a
manual use case to implement
an abstract factory and this is the case of
super mario maker
[Music]
friends
well everything
[Music]
ah
in super mario maker you can mount well
your own supermario levels the
typical ones  levels of the gameboy or
the nintendo ds putting
typical elements of the saga such as
pipes enemies and blocks but not only
that but one of the characteristics
of the game and why it became so
famous is that it allows to modify the
visual style of the level using
classic game boy graphics or
nintendo ds graphics with the same level but
with a different visualization in this
way the players can choose the
style that best fits with their levels
but how do they do this how does it work one
of the ways to do it would be
precisely using an
abstract factory let's see how first let's
see what problems we can
encounter if we try to achieve this
functionality but
simply using the factor pattern and let's say we have
a factor and that it
instantiates objects from the question mark block class
according to the style of the level it
can instantiate elements of the
concrete game boy question mark
nintendo of that question mark although in
reality we should not care what is
important is that it is a question
mark block we have our nice
factory and it is the one we use to
distance these elements that at the
moment are the only ones that change
depending on the type of level if we want
for example the coins to also
change style we will have to
build another factor and a factor  and
for the coins class that instantiates
the currency corresponding to the type of
level we have in front of us you see where we are
going if we continue down this path we will
have a factor and for each element
that we want to be affected in total we will
end up having a lot of
factories and we have to manage
more and more classes in addition all this
brings another problem and that is that by offering
all the factories individually there
is no control system over
which items are used with which nothing would
prevent that in a certain part of the code
a lying down is instantiated when the
level style
is 3d to solve this enter the
abstract factory the abstract factory
is defined as and let me read the
formal definition design pattern that
provides an interface now to create
families of related or
dependent objects without specifying their
concrete class provides an interface to
create is a creation pattern for families
of related or dependent objects
related objects like the
mario maker example where they are related by
themes by visual style there are
objects with game boy graphics on one
hand and objects with
nintendo ds graphics on the other and I want to
emphasize that its
concrete class is not specified, that is to say, it continues
working 100%  with abstractions you never
depend on a specific class of currency you
always use the currency abstraction
so that it makes no difference to you if it's a
Game Boy coin or a
Nintendo DS coin or a Girl coin and you don't care
with this we get the good thing about
factories which is to work independently on
specific actions for each class but it
also allows us to create relationships
between objects so that they can't be
used indiscriminately it
protects you from accidentally using objects
that shouldn't be used together and setting
up that whole thing isn't that
difficult either it's a bit confusing but not
difficult instead of having a factory with
a method to create a certain object we have
an abstract factory that has several
methods that create different types of
objects in the example we are looking at
the abstract factory would have defined
the method to create a question mark block and
the method to create currency would be the responsibility
of the specific implementation of this
abstract factorial factory implementing
these methods and creating
specific instances of these objects
for example we would have the
abstract factory envoy maps track factory
that always instantiates the
specific classes that implement the graphics
see in boyle and we would have the same with
the  nintendo ds filmax track factory that
would implement these same methods but
instance cndh or the concrete classes
that implement the internal graphics
is
and to avoid giving us so much we are going to
put another example this time a little
applied to the development of
multiplatform applications we have all heard
of rhinitis fruit bowl that allows you to
develop applications for both
android and adults if we see the
same application made for example in
platter in ios or android we will surely
see that the graphic elements are
different the buttons or the
text inputs because they change from one platform to
another a possible implementation of this
feature at the framework level
since in the multiplatform application it
could be to use abstract factories
having a specific abstract factory
of ios elements and another of
android elements even another example could
be the famous dark film that they are
taking out now to many applications the
dark theme can also be implemented
using abstract factories
following the same logic one
implementation creates elements in a
light mode and the other implementation creates
elements in dark mode let's see the
vml diagram now on screen to
finish understanding these examples and see
a little bit of the formality
we have the abstract class or
abstract factory interface that would be the one that
defines the factory methods with the
abstract class that builds the method
that creates coins the method that creates
question marks blocks etcetera and on the
other hand we have the individual products
the products would be on the one hand the
abstractions, that is to say coin and
question mark block what really generates
dependencies and underneath the
concrete classes the gameboy coin or the
nintendo ds coin for example is the
responsibility of each
concrete abstract factory that inherits or
implements the general abstract factory it
instantiates some classes or others
but from the outside you never know nor
should you know what concrete class
you are working with that is why you always
work with these abstractions
these abstract classes you are interface
just whatever let's use
polymorphism heavily and basically this is it I have
tried to give a little more variety to
the examples because to finish
understanding the reason for this pattern and how it
can be applied to different cases
I hope you
liked the video and you know
subscribe and give the like if you like
this series
thank you very much for watching me and see you in
the next video bye